Finding Aid for Saint Francis Prayer Center (Flint, Mich.) records, 1993-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Saint Francis Prayer Center (Flint, Mich.) records 1993-2001
Saint Francis Prayer Center (Flint, Mich.)
0467 Ba 2
The records of the Saint Francis Prayer Center document the Center's activities with regards to environmental justice particularly in the 1990s when it was deeply involved (as a plaintiff) in two important legal cases: NAACP v. Engler and the Select Steel Case. The bulk of the collection consists of legal documents, correspondence, and reports produced during these two cases.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
These records were donated by the Center (donor no. 9422 ) on January 7, 2004.
The record group is open to research.
The Saint Francis Prayer Center of Flint, Michigan is a donation supported Catholic retreat center founded in 1975 by Father Philip Schmitter and Sister Joanne Chiaverini. The goals of the Saint Francis Prayer Center were to provide a central location for the local community to walk, to provide spiritual guidance, and to bridge gaps that exists between religious and racial lines. Over the years the Fr. Schmitter and Sr. Chiaverini have expanded the mission of the Center to include advocacy on environmental justice issues facing Flint.
The Saint Francis Prayer Center was deeply involved in two important legal cases regarding environmental justice and racism. In NAACP v. John Engler et al. the Center was a plaintiff in the attempt to close the Genesee Power Station in Flint. It was also a part of a 1998 filing of a Title VI complaint (part of the Civil Rights Act of 1964) which claimed that the construction of the Select Steel Mill violated the civil rights of the residents in Flint.
In 1993 the Department of Environmental Quality (MDEQ) issued a permit to the Genesee Power Station, whose fuel supply included construction and demolition wood containing lead based paint. The permit allowed lead emissions of 2.4 tons per year into the local, already highly polluted, mostly African-American community. After several years of litigation the court issued an injunction prohibiting the State of Michigan from granting any more permits until it had reformed its system of environmental protections, including requirements that the state perform risk assessments and reform its public hearing process, which the court found was not "meaningful." Throughout this process the Saint Francis Prayer Center opened its doors to the litigation team of the Sugar Law Center and Fr. Schmitter and Sr. Chiaverini were highly involved in the legal process, appearing at trial every day.
In June of 1998, the MDEQ granted a permit to the Select Steel Corporation to build a steel recycling plant in northern Flint, Michigan, again adjacent to a largely African-American neighborhood. The residents of the community, along with two community-based organizations filed a Title VI administrative complaint. In August 1998, the EPA Office of Civil Rights accepted the complaint for investigation. On October 30, 1998, 74 days after it accepted the Select Steel complaint, the OCR issued its first and only substantive Title VI decision in the 25 years that EPA's paragraph 602 regulations had been in effect. In its decision, the EPA found no Title VI violation and ruled in favor of the State. In March, 1999, sixteen, of the more than 20 groups of complainants from the still-pending administrative actions, jointly filed a Petition with the EPA seeking to have the Select Steel decision reconsidered. This appeal was also denied.
These important cases as well as other community issues in which the Center has been involved demonstrate the commitment that the staff at the Saint Francis Prayer Center has to issues of environmental justice and community well-being. The Saint Francis Prayer Center continues to be a source of spiritual and material assistance to the city of Flint and the surrounding area.
The records of the Saint Francis Prayer Center document the activities of this organization particularly in its efforts to fight environmental racism the during the decade of the 1990s. This collection is organized into three series which represent two of the most important legal and political battles in which the Saint Francis Prayer Center has participated as well as other activities. The series in the record group are: Genesee County Power Station; Select Steel Plant; and Other Activities.
Subjects:
Saint Francis Prayer Center (Flint, Mich.); Catholic Church--Michigan--Flint.; Environmental justice--Michigan--Flint.; Flint (Mich.); Genesee Power Station.; Select Steel Corporation of America.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Genesee County Power Station 1992-2000
  The Genesee County Power Station series, 1992 to 2000, (approximately 1.25 linear feet) consists mostly of legal documents, correspondence, and reports produced by the Saint Francis Prayer Center's participation in NAACP-Flint Chapter et al. v. John Engler et al in an attempt to close down the Genesee County Power Station This series is divided into five sub-series: Legal Documents, Correspondence, Reports/Applications, Meetings, and Miscellaneous. The materials within these sub-series are organized chronologically
  - Legal Documents
    - US EPA Environmental Appeals Board
      - Petition of the American Lung Association of Michigan To Environmental Appeals Board US EPA January 5, 1993 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 1)
      - Response to Petitions for Review of PSD Permit of Genesee Power Station Limited Partnership February 24, 1993 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 2)
      - Order Denying Review in Part and Remanding in Part September 8, 1993 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 3)
      - Genesee Power Station Response to EPA Appeal 1993 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 4)
      - Order on Motion for Clarification October 22, 1993 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 5)
      - Letter to Dan J. Rondeau, EPA Director October 19, 1994 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 6)
      - Letter to Michael Mathieson and Carlton Waterhouse, US EPA Office of Civil Rights re: Title VI Complaint, State of Michigan February 10, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 7)
      - MDEQ Stipulation for Entry of Final Order By Consent 1998, 1999 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 8)
    - NAACP-Flint Chapter, et al. v. John Engler, et al
      - Brief in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Injunctive Relief July 11, 1995 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 9)
      - Letter to Judge Vladimer Washington September 29, 1995 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 10)
      - Affidavit of Sister Joanne Chiaverini October 12, 1995 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 11)
      - Consent Judgment Between Plaintiffs And Defendant Genesee Power Station Limited Partnership February 2, 1996 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 12)
      - Defendant Genesee Power Station Limited Partnership Brief in Support of Motion to Enforce Consent Judgment and for Order to Show Cause Why an Order of Contempt Should Not Issue Against Plaintiffs Counsel October 1, 1996 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 13)
      - Exhibits to Plaintiffs First Motion For Summary Disposition, A-D (Box 1)
        (folder no. 14)
      - Exhibits to Plaintiffs First Motion For Summary Disposition, E-H (Box 1)
        (folder no. 15)
      - Deposition of Russell J. Harding October 17, 1996 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 16)
      - Various Motions 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 17)
      - Deposition of Kimberly Armbruster February 10, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 18)
      - Plaintiffs' First Motion For Partial Summary Judgment March 24, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 19)
      - Plaintiffs' Brief in Support of First Motion for Partial Summary Judgment March 24, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 20)
      - Transcript of Motion Before the Honorable Archie L. Hayman March 29, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 21)
      - Transcript of Motion Before the Honorable Archie L. Hayman March 31, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 22)
      - Plaintiffs' Objections to Defendant's Proposed Order May 29, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 23)
      - Order Granting Plaintiffs' Motion for a Permanent Injunction 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 24)
      - Transcript of Motion Before the Honorable Archie L. Hayman May 29, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 25)
      - Plaintiffs' Motion for Evidentiary Hearing Regarding Scope of Relief June 18, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 26)
      - Plaintiffs' Brief in Support of Motion For Evidentiary Hearing Regarding Scope of Relief June 18, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 27)
      - Plaintiffs' Motion to Amend the Pleadings to Add Claims Under Articles 51 and 52 of the Michigan Constitution and Under Part 55 of Michigan's Natural Resources and Environmental Protection Act June 19, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 28)
      - Brief in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion to Amend the Pleadings to Add Claims Under Articles 51 and 52 of the Michigan Constitution and Under Part 55 of Michigan's Natural Resources and Environmental Protection Act June 19, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 29)
      - Plaintiffs' Motion to Amend Conclusion of Law Under MCR 2.517(B) June 19, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 30)
      - Brief in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion to Amend Conclusion of Law Under MCR 2.517(B) June 19, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 31)
      - Plaintiffs' Third Amended Complaint and Request for Injunctive Relief June 19, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 32)
      - Transcript of Motion Before the Honorable Archie L. Hayman June 30, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 33)
      - Plaintiffs' Motion to Strike Genesee Power Station Limited Partnership's Submission Requesting Correction of the Record And to Award Plaintiffs Costs and Fees Incurred in Defending Against Genesee's Submission July 23, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 34)
      - Brief in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion to Strike Genesee Power Station Limited Partnership's Submission Requesting Correction of the Record And to Award Plaintiffs Costs and Fees Incurred in Defending Against Genesee's Submission July 23, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 35)
      - Written Orders of Judge Hayman 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 36)
      - Plaintiffs' Verified Bill of Costs August 21, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 37)
      - Plaintiff's First Motion for Costs August 21, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 38)
      - Notice of Hearing August 22, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 39)
      - Brief in Support of Plaintiff's First Motion for Costs August 21, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 40)
      - Plaintiffs'-Appellees' Brief in Opposition to State Defendant's Motion for Stay of Injunctive Orders and For Immediate Consideration of Motion for Stay September 20, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 41)
      - Plaintiffs' Answer to Defendant's Motion for Stay and for Immediate Consideration September 20, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 42)
      - Plaintiffs'-Appellees' Reply in Opposition to State Defendant's Appeal October 30, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 43)
      - Plaintiffs'-Appellees' Motion to File Plaintiffs'-Appellees' Reply Brief to State Defendant's Appeal October 31, 1997 Order, 1997 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 44)
      - Plaintiffs' Brief in Support of Cross Appeal January 12, 1998 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 45)
      - Per Curium Ruling November 30, 1998 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 46)
      - Plaintiffs-Appellees'/Cross-Appellants' Motion for Rehearing December 14, 1998 (Box 1)
        (folder no. 47)
  - Correspondence
    - 1985-1991 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 48)
    - 1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (folders nos. 49-50)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 51)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 52)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 53)
    - 1997 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 54)
    - 1998 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 55)
    - 1999 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 56)
    - 2000 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 57)
    - FOIA requests 1992-1993 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 58)
    - FOIA requests 1997 (Box 1)
      (folder no. 59)
  - Reports/Applications
    - Application June 8, 1992 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 60)
    - Wood Fuel Study Final Report Draft July 17, 1992 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 61)
    - MDNR Air Quality Division Staff Activity Report October 27, 1992 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 62)
    - DNR Air Quality Division Staff Activity Report Addendum December 1, 1992 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 63)
    - Environmental Inequality in Action, Winter 1993 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 64)
    - Wood Waste Procurement and Monitoring Plan August 17, 1994 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 65)
    - Wood Waste Procurement and Monitoring Plan, Final Plan December 1, 1994 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 66)
    - An Analysis of Emissions and Impacts for the Genesee Wood Waste Boiler May 2, 1995 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 67)
    - Report from the Special Master February 6, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 68)
    - Emission Minimization Plan for Start-up and Shutdown, Genesee Power Station Limited Partnership December 21, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 69)
    - Preventative Maintenance & Malfunction Abatement Plan for Boiler, SNCR, Mechanical Dust Collector, Precipitator, and CEM Equipment, revision 4 April 1999 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 70)
    - Revision number 5 April 19, 1999 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 71)
  - Meetings 1992-1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (folders nos. 72-73)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Flyers (Box 2)
      (folder no. 74)
    - News Clippings 1992-1996 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 75)
    - Neighborhood Response (Box 2)
      (folder no. 76)
    - Slide Presentation to Air Quality Control Commission December 1, 1992 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 77)
    - "Toxic Tour" (Box 2)
      (folder no. 78)
- Select Steel Plant 1998-1999
  The Select Steel Plant series, 1998-1999 (approximately .5 linear feet) also contains legal documents, correspondence, and reports produced by the Saint Francis Prayer Center's efforts to prevent the construction of the Select Steel Plant in Flint Michigan on the grounds that it would violate the civil rights of the residents living in the area.
  - Legal Documents
    - Environmental Appeals Board US EPA Response of the Michigan Department of Environmental Quality to the Petition of The St. Francis Prayer Center August 19, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 79)
    - Environmental Appeals Board US EPA Order Denying Review September 10, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 80)
    - MDEQ Response to St. Francis Prayer Center Title VI Complaint of June 9, 1998 Regarding Select Steel, September 16, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 81)
    - Joint Petition to Re-open Select Steel Investigation, or, in the Alternative, to Set Aside Investigative and Analytical Methods (Box 2)
      (folder no. 82)
    - Schedule of Exhibits, A-T, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (folders nos. 83-84)
    - Transcript of Lillian Robinson, United for Action, before the National Environmental Justice Advisory Committee December 7-10, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 85)
  - Correspondence
    - 1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (folders nos. 86-87)
    - 1999 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 88)
    - Sagady, A. J. 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 89)
    - FOIA requests 1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (folders nos. 90-91)
  - Reports/Applications
    - Michigan Air Use Permit Application for Select Steel Company, Flint, Michigan December 1997 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 92)
    - MDEQ Air Quality Division Staff Activity Report March 23, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 93)
    - Evaluation of the Potential Dry Deposition and Children's Exposure to Lead Emissions From the Proposed Select Steel Facility May 15, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 94)
    - Select Steel Corporation of America Response to Comments Document May 27, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 95)
    - Supplement to Permit no. 579-97, Select Steel Corporation of America, Flint, Michigan May 27, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 96)
    - US EPA Office of Civil Rights Investigative Report for Title VI Administrative Complaint File No. 5R-98-R5 (Select Steel Complaint) (Box 2)
      (folder no. 97)
    - An Assessment of Disparate Impacts to Minority and Low-Income Populations in the Vicinity of the Proposed Select Steel Mill in Genesee County, Michigan, Addendum October 26, 1998 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 98)
    - Written Statement of Julie H. Hurwitz, NLG/Sugar Law Center Environmental Justice Symposium, May, 25 1999 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 99)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Flyers (Box 2)
      (folder no. 100)
    - News Clippings 1998-1999 (Box 2)
      (folder no. 101)
- Other Activities 1993-1998
  The Other Activities series, 1993-1998, (approximately .25 linear feet) contains materials related to a few of the other activities that the Saint Francis Prayer Centers performs. It contains the articles of Incorporation, correspondence, and miscellaneous materials relating to other community activities.
  - Articles of Incorporation 1993 (Box 2)
    (folder no. 102)
  - Correspondence 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    (folder no. 103)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    (folder no. 104)